《太空堡垒卡拉狄加》 前情提要
ADAMA: Previously on Battlestar Galactica.
你不能在扮演上帝后  又对你创造的东西不负责任
You cannot play God then wash your hands of the things that you've created.
迟早  这一天终会来临
Sooner or later, the day comes
那时你将无法回避你所做过的事情
when you can't hide from the things that you've done anymore.
所有殖民地军事单位注意
"Attention all colonial units.
我们受到赛昂人袭击
"Cylon attack underway.
这不是演习
"This is no drill. "
我马上就过去
I'll be right there.
怎么会?为什么?
How? Why?
已经不再重要
It doesn't really matter now.
重要的是  此时此刻
What does matter is that, as of this moment,
战争开始了
we are at war.
你满肚子都是怒火、仇恨
ADAMA: You're full of bile, hatred,
酒精
poison.
对于你在地面上发生的事  我很抱歉
And I'm sorry for what happened to you down there,
但我要管理整艘船
but I gotta run a ship.
我不能忍受一个独眼的醉鬼
The last thing I need
在这儿坐着  还散播不满
is a one-eyed drunk sowing discontent and disobedience.
把你的屁股挪回你的地方并且不要再离开
So you can get your ass back into your quarters and not leave
直到你表现得 像我在过去30年里认识的那个男人
until you're ready to act like the man that I've known for the past 30 years.
那个人不会再存在了  比尔
That man doesn't exist anymore, Bill.
你也不会再见到我了
You won't be seeing me again.
不知道在宇宙里  是否有一个地方
Is there really any place left in the universe
能放置这样的一个名贵物品?
deserving of such a rare and distinguished item?
我在想把它放在卫生间里 正正地摆在厕所上面
I was thinking put it in the bathroom, right over the toilet.
非常好的决定
Excellent choice.
噢  我的天啊
Oh, my Gods.
噢  托瑞  过来看看  这个档案是比利
Tory, come look at this. This is the dossier
在我登上卡拉狄加的第一天给我准备的
that Billy prepared for me my first day aboard Galactica.
真不敢想象我刚才差点把它丢垃圾桶里了
I can't believe I was about to throw this out in the trash.
瓦尔基里号
TORY: The Valkyrie.
这是阿达玛指挥官在卡拉狄加号之前指挥的吗?
This was Adama's command before Galactica? Mmm-hmm.
看这里
Look at that.
今年是阿达玛上将
This year marks Admiral Adama's
在殖民地联邦舰队服役45周年纪念
45th anniversary in the Colonial Fleet.
实际上  他的入伍纪念日就在最近几天
In fact, his commissioning date's only a few days from now.
帮我拿着
Here.
我想举办一个庆祝仪式
I think I want to have a ceremony.
让我们给上将颁个勋章
Let's give the Admiral a medal
纪念他45年来的卓越贡献
for 45 years of devoted service.
这是个再好不过的日子啦
Couldn't have come at a better time.
让大家共同感受一下这种气氛吧
Give the people something to feel good about for a change.
我是副长 全舰进入一级戒备状态
HELO ON PA: This is the XO. Set Condition 1 throughout the ship.
重复 全舰进入一级戒备状态
I repeat, set condition one throughout the ship.
这不是演习
This is not a drill.
有什么情况?      有三架突袭机
What's the problem? Three Raiders.
正在持续接近  方向145  定位33
CBDR, bearing 145, carom 33.
但这不是他们的标准编队方式
But this isn't their standard wedge formation.
我们的CAP编队在哪?
Where's the CAP?
星芭和凯特会在98秒内拦截  长官
Starbuck and Kat will intercept in 98 seconds, sir.
他们看起来像是在追击同时还在交火
It looks like a pursuit and there's been weapons exchange between them.
追击?        是的  长官
A pursuit? Yes, sir.
看上去是两架突袭机在追击另一架
We've got two Raiders chasing a third.
他们有没有向我们开火?
Have they fired on any of ours yet?
没有  长官
No, sir.
他妈的他们在干吗?
What the hell are they doing?
好啦 让我们过去凑凑热闹 先不用开火
All right, let's see if we can climb up their asses without drawing any fire.
追击的那两架看起来对逃的那架很专注呢
These two seem pretty preoccupied with the other one.
对赛昂人之间的追击有什么看法呢?
Got any idea why Cylons would be chasing Cylons?
不知道  不关心
Don't know, don't care.
要等靠近了再说
But wait till we close the gap.
我可不想等得超出我的忍耐程度
I don't wanna chase these frakking things any longer than I have to.
是  收到
Yeah, roger that.
干掉了两架!  还有一架在逃!        凯特  关注六点钟方向
KAT: Two down! One to go! STARBUCK: Kat, check six.
该死的  凯特  是右侧  这架准备朝卡拉狄加飞去
Damn, Kat, flank right. This guy's headed right for Galactica.
我会跟上的  长官!
I'm on it, Starbuck.
紧急求救 紧急求救 紧急求救
NOVACEK ON RADIO: Krypter! Krypter! Krypter!
我是大狗
This is Bulldog.
快把我从这里救出去 我受伤了!
Get me the hell out of here. I'm wounded!
这是什么该死的东西?      目标进入射程 快包围
STARBUCK: What the frak is that? KAT: Target in range, closing in.
紧急求救  紧急求救  紧急求救  我是大狗
NOVACEK: Krypter! Krypter! Krypter! This is Bulldog...
音频自动追踪开启
KELLY: Audio lock-on enabled.
那东西是从哪来的?
Where is that coming from?
那是架突袭机  长官
GAETA: It's the Raider, sir.
紧急求救        快开火  凯特
NOVACEK: Krypter... STARBUCK: Take the frakking shot, Kat.
等下 我快和他联系上了
KAT: Gimme one sec, I almost got him lined up.
紧急求救 紧急求救 紧急求救
NOVACEK: Krypter! Krypter! Krypter!
我是大狗
This is Bulldog.
凯特  赶快射击!
STARBUCK: Kat, take the frakking shot.
命令蝮蛇战机停止射击
Order the Vipers to hold their fire immediately.
马上保护这架突袭机入舱
Have them escort the Raider in.
准备好监狱
Prisoner drill.
在飞行甲板设置警卫 5分钟内办完
I want the alert guard in the hangar deck in five minutes.
是  长官
Yes, sir.
好了  把那只"小鸟"停好!  让我们看看这架突袭机!
All right, park that bird! Let's grab this Raider!
大伙跟我上! 快点跟上来!
Let's go, people, move with a purpose!
给陆战队腾地方
Make some room for the Marines.
真的是你吗  长官?
Is it really you, sir?
是的
Yeah,
是我
it's me.
欢迎回家  大狗
Welcome home, Bulldog.
我们不会再有第二次机会了
We may never have this opportunity again.
我猜如果发现赛昂人的问题后
I'm assuming you appreciate the consequences
你会感激这个决定的
if you're discovered.
并且你也该知道  指挥官
And you understand, Commander,
我们刚才的谈话是没有发生过的
that this conversation did not happen.
你想好了吗?
Are you prepared for this?
当然  长官
Of course, sir.
但有一个条件:
On one condition.
我要用我自己的人
I need my men.
尤其是要驾驶这艘秘密行动飞船的
Especially for the stealth ship.
只有一个飞行员是我能信任的
There's only one pilot I trust.
谁?
Who?
很好
Well,
持阴谋论者会大失所望的
the conspiracy theorists are gonna be disappointed.
我们已检查过你的DNA序列  与你在军队的纪录对比
We've checked your DNA signature against your military records,
结果是很明确的
and it's conclusive.
你不是赛昂人
You're not a Cylon.
抽烟吗?
Smoke?
没错
That's right.
他是我的人
He's one of mine.
三年前失踪的
Disappeared about three years ago.
我们以为他被抓了
We think that he was captured.
我想见见他
I'd like to meet him.
当然可以 我会安排的
Of course. I'll arrange it.
他的检查没有问题
He checks out fine.
不管他们对他做过些什么
Whatever they did to him out there,
他们还是保证了他相对的健康程度
they kept him fed and relatively healthy.
总之  身体是健康的
Physically, anyway.
我知道你遭受了很多磨难
I know you've been through a lot.
我承认
I realize that.
但你必须告诉我  丹尼尔
But you've gotta talk to me, Danny.
你究竟是如何
How the hell did you escape
从赛昂人的基地之星逃出来的?
off a Cylon baseship?
好吧  长官
Well, sir,
是这样的
it's like this.
敌人将我在监狱里囚禁了三年
The enemy had me locked in a cell for three years.
住宿条件很恶劣
The accommodations were lousy,
食物供给都跟不上了
the service was slow,
当我感觉到他们不再打算向我供给任何东西时
and after a while I felt the institution no longer had anything to offer me.
我就离开了
So I left.
你让我担心了好长一段时间
You had me worried there for a moment.
也想到  也许赛昂人被你的那种态度打败了
Thought maybe the Cylons had beaten the bullshit attitude out of you.
你是怎么出来的?
How'd you get out?
我以为我会死在那里  比尔
I thought I was gonna die in there, Bill.
但是不久前  他们突然都得病了
But a while ago, they all started getting sick.
我意思是真的病得很重
I mean really sick.
你是说有病毒?
You mean a virus?
是的
Yeah.
我们也知道
We've seen that, too.
我听到他们说病毒在扩散 情况在变糟…
I heard them say it was spreading, getting worse,
但是同时我也认识到
but eventually I realize,
我是不会被感染的
I'm not catching it.
我对它是免疫的
I'm immune.
那后来呢?
So what did you do?
我很聪明
I was smart,
很有耐心
patient.
我等待
I waited.
啊  很好呀
D'ANNA: Well, well.
你看起来不错
You're looking good.
强壮
Strong.
我...我已经感觉好些了
Me, I've felt better.
我不知道你这家伙为什么要锻炼身体
I don't know why you guys do all that exercise.
为什么呢  你在为了预防衰老?
What, are you trying to stave off getting old?
没看到我有多悲惨吗?
Doesn't seem such a tragedy to me,
给你个机会选择
given the alternatives.
你知道我说什么吗?
You know what I'm saying?
我看起来那么坏吗?
Do I look that bad?
你知道我在想什么吗?
You know what I think?
我想你在害怕
I think you're afraid.
让我来猜猜在你身上到底发生了什么
Let me try and understand exactly what happened to you.
我只准备回忆一小段
I'm just gonna go back a little,
如何?
all right?
在赛昂人攻击殖民地联邦的一年前
About a year prior to the Cylon attack on the Colonies,
你正在执行阿达玛上将的一项任务 对吗?
you were on a mission with Admiral Adama. Is that correct?
那是个秘密任务
It was a black ops mission.
嗯
Hmm.
你记得那些陶伦殖民地的人经常干些不法的事情
You remember the Tauron colonists were such outlaws,
还经常与舰队玩捉迷藏 以此得到他们想要的?
always pushing their luck with the Admiralty every chance they got?
对
ROSLIN: Right.
陶伦人在一个卫星上开采泰里恩矿
The Taurons were drilling for tylium ore
那颗卫星离赛昂人的停火线很近
on a moon that was too close to the Cylon armistice line.
我们觉得必须让他们从那里离开
We knew that they had to get out of there
否则就会激怒赛昂人
or risk provoking the Cylons.
对不起  但这个事情与他的飞船被击落有什么关系?
I'm sorry, but how did this result in his ship being shot down?
他是我的侦查机飞行员
He was my recon pilot.
他去那里收集证据
He was there to gather evidence.
陶伦人一定是看到我们来了 因为他们围攻他
The Taurons must have seen us coming, because they ambushed him.
那维克中尉
Lieutenant Novacek was shot down
被陶伦人冷血地击落
by the Taurons in cold blood.
紧急求救  紧急求救  紧急求救  我左舷引擎损坏
NOVACEK: Krypter! Krypter! Krypter! I've got damage to the port engine.
正在坠落  重复
Bird is down. Repeat,
正在坠落 请求救助
bird is down. Request rescue.
秘密之星传来的信息       我是大狗
MAN: Stealthstar transmission acquired. NOVACEK: This is Bulldog,
我在坠落 重复
bird is down. Repeat,
我在坠落 请求救助
bird is down. Request rescue.
那你当时做了什么?
So what did you do?
我判断错误
I made a bad call.
以为船已坠毁
His ship was gone.
雷达没有弹射座椅信号
No ejection on dradis.
也没有求救信号
No distress call.
以为他已经死了
He was dead,
然后我们就离开了
so I left.
但很明显  中尉的座椅弹射出来了 并且还幸免遇难
But the lieutenant did eject, obviously, and somehow survived
在他的弹射座椅中待了足够长的时间
in his ejection seat long enough
这还让赛昂人找到他了
for the Cylons to find him.
哇
Wow.
你们能让我考虑一下吗?
Could you both give us a moment, please?
谢谢你  托瑞  非常谢谢你  中尉
Thank you, Tory, and thank you very much, Lieutenant,
我很感谢 总统女士
I appreciate it. Madam President.
让我们查查舰队的登记名册
Why don't we check the fleet registry,
看看你是否还有家人生还  好吗?
see if any of your family might have survived?
好的 现在你能告诉我到底发生了什么吗?
So, are you gonna tell me what really happened?
这个事情你一定要相信我  好吗?
You're gonna have to trust me on this one, okay?
这是我捅出的娄子
It's my mess.
我会弥补的
I'll fix it.
好吧 这是最后一次    对
Okay, this is the last one. Yeah.
开火
Fire.
我知道了
TIGH: I see it.
I see it.
我知道了
丹尼尔 那维克刚逃出来了
Daniel Novacek
从赛昂人的一艘基地之星的监狱里逃出来了
just escaped from a POW cell on a Cylon baseship,
偷了一架突袭机  飞回来了
stole a Raider, flew it here.
我刚才给他做个终结报告
I just finished debriefing him.
大狗还活着?
Bulldog's alive?
是啊
Yeah.
我的天
My Gods.
他是怎么活下来的?
How could he be alive?
那个坚强的臭小子 他最后成功了 是不是?
That tough son of a bitch, he actually made it, didn't he?
是的  我猜他是成功了
Yeah, I guess he did.
那你过来是跟你的朋友说 还是跟你的副长说?
So, are you here to talk to your friend or to your XO?
我想这次  都不是
And last time I checked, I was neither.
我懂了
Oh... I get it.
噢  是啊
Oh, yeah.
这对你有一点点复杂  对吗  上将?
This is gonna be a little complicated for you, isn't it, Admiral?
你要告诉他  你做了什么?
You gonna tell him what you did?
我做了我必须该做的
I did what I had to do.
那就告诉他
So tell him.
但这并不改变任何结果 过去的事情就过去了
It's not gonna make any difference. The past is the past.
你支支吾吾的
You're equivocating.
我不知道我来这该死的地方干嘛  告诉他!
I don't know why the frak I came here. Tell him!
他会知道的
He's gonna find out
迟早的事
sooner or later.
我知道了
I see it.
走开
Go away.
他妈的该死的家伙
Gods damn son of a bitch.
我真不敢想象
I can't believe it.
真的是你
It's really you.
丹尼尔 那维克
Danny Novacek.
他们告诉我你成功逃了出来
I heard you'd made it.
干得好  大狗
Good for you, Bulldog.
哦 天啊
Oh, Gods.
少
Saul.
来点酒?
A drink?
这主意不错
You have no idea.
是啊  确实不错
Yes, I do.
爸爸?
Dad?
嘿  我刚接到你的通知
Hey, I just got your message.
谢谢你过来
Thank you for coming.
坐下
Sit down.
该是我们聊聊的时候了
It's time for us to talk.
我问你几个问题
Let me ask you something.
你经常来卡拉狄加吗?
How often you get out of here?
为什么这么问   一直在这啊
Why? All the time.
我正在经历着一些麻烦 就这样
I've been a little under the weather, that's all.
那你是一直待在这个老水桶里来着?
And how'd you wind up on this old bucket anyway?
瓦尔基里号怎么了?
What happened to the Valkyrie?
好吧  嗯  那我们就说说
Well, let's just say
那次任务对老头子职业生涯来说 并不是什么好事
that last mission wasn't exactly a boon to the old man's career.
卡拉狄加就是他最后光荣的退役
Galactica was his graceful retirement.
听说你和老头子好长时间不说话了
Heard you and the old man haven't spoken in a while.
怎么了?
What's wrong?
他不再像过去那样跟你穿一条裤子了吧?
He won't cover your ass day and night like he used to?
噢  不  他还在跟我穿一条裤子呢
Oh, no, he still does his share of ass-covering.
问题是  那是他应该的
Problem is, it's his main function now.
当然了
Of course,
考虑到你在那里受伤并被抓
considering how you wound up getting captured in the first place,
我猜你自己想离开的话并不太容易  对吧?
I guess you found that out the hard way yourself, didn't you?
你想说什么?
What's that supposed to mean?
我的天
My Gods.
他没有告诉你  是不是？
He didn't tell you, did he?
是不是?
Did he?
跟我说什么?
Tell me what?
那个狗娘养的
That son of a bitch.
是我把他射下来的
I shot him down.
那好  如果是你射下的他  那你一定有你的理由
Well, if you shot him down, you had your reasons.
你在执行命令
You were following orders,
担心更糟糕的事情发生  对吗?
preventing something worse, right?
不是
No.
我把他射下来是为了防止...
I shot him down to avoid
防止他被发现
detection.
确保任务保密
Protect the mission,
那他就不会被赛昂人发现
so it wouldn't be discovered by the Cylons.
那是个秘密任务
It was a black ops mission
目的是...
whose sole purpose
是确认赛昂人攻击的可能性
was to ascertain the likelihood of a Cylon strike.
赛昂人的攻击?
"Cylon strike"?
那你是在说...
So, you're saying that...
我们在过去就知道它们准备攻击了
That we knew they were out there?
它们可能准备发动针对殖民地联邦的攻击?
That they could launch an attack on the Colonies?
我们没有确切的信息
We didn't know anything for sure.
有些人是这样认为的
There were theories in some circles
赛昂人隐匿那么久的原因
that the reason that the Cylons had stayed dormant for so long
是因为他们在建造战争机器
was because they were building a war machine,
在准备攻击我们
preparing a strike.
但我认为...
But I thought...
没人见到或听说赛昂人了 将近40年了
I thought that no one had seen or heard from the Cylons in over 40 years.
那是对的 相对的
That's true, partially.
阿达尔政权领导下的军部对此深感不安
The Admiralty had grown restless with the Adar administration.
他们认为我们现在在吃老本
They thought we were resting on our laurels,
没有准备好保护人们免于攻击
unprepared to protect against an attack.
我的任务是派遣一艘秘密侦察船
My mission was to escort a stealth recon ship
越过停火线
just beyond the armistice line.
仔细观察  收集证据
Stick our nose over, gather evidence,
看看他们有没有任何可疑的行动
see if there was any suspicious activities.
那如果赛昂人发现你们越过停火线
And if the Cylons discovered you had crossed the line,
违背停战协议  那他们可以把这种行为视为…
breaching the armistice, then they would see that as...
战争行为
An act of war.
秘密之星  这里是瓦尔基里号  我们在雷达上监测到
MAN: Stealthstar, Valkyrie. We register you on dradis,
你刚刚越过停火线
just past the armistice line.
你要提高警惕 谨慎行动
You're on full alert. Proceed with caution.
瓦尔基里号 我是大狗
Valkyrie, Bulldog.
我刚过了停火线两公里远
I'm exactly two clicks past the line.
重复 两公里远 并且我的雷达上
Repeat, two clicks and I've got
没有任何反应
negative dradis contacts.
没有东西 长官
Sir, there's nothing here, sir.
看来我运气不错
Which is fine by me.
公费旅行 你们找对机师了
Company wants to pay me for a joyride, they came to the right driver.
一颗很大的卫星
Hell of a moon.
雷达发现目标 有未知飞船跳跃过来
MAN: Dradis contact. Unknown vessel just jumped in.
妈的!
Frak!
紧急求救  我左舷引擎损坏
Krypter! Krypter! Krypter! I've got damage to the port engine.
正在坠落 重复  正在坠落
Bird is down. Repeat, bird is down.
请求救助
Request rescue.
紧急求救 我是大狗
Krypter! Krypter! Krypter! This is Bulldog.
那艘飞船刚跳跃走  长官
MAN: Vessel just jumped out, sir.
我在坠落 请求救助
NOVACEK: Bird is down. Request rescue.
紧急求救 我是大狗
Krypter! Krypter! Krypter! This is Bulldog.
正在坠落 重复
Bird is down! Repeat.
雷达发现另外两个目标 长官  请指示
MAN: Two more dradis contacts. Sir, please instruct.
您有什么命令  长官？
What are your orders, sir?
长官  您有什么命令?
Sir, what are your orders?
不要这么做
TIGH: Don't do this.
要考虑清楚  比尔  你不会这么干的
Think about it, Bill. You don't want to do this.
你想让他的船被发现吗?
Do you want his ship discovered?
你知道我们现在在哪吗?
Do you know where we are?
你知不知道这会有什么后果?
Do you have any idea what this could mean?
未知飞船正在拦截航线上
MAN: Bogies on intercept course.
将在20秒内抵达秘密之星
Will merge with Stealthstar in 20 seconds.
长官?
Sir?
武器
Weapons,
发射舰对舰导弹  马上!
launch ship-to-ship missile, now.
不!
No!
这不可能    噢  那就是事实
There is no way... Oh, it's true.
并且你也知道那是真的
And you know it's true.
在那以后  你每时每刻都知道
You've known it every second of every day since it happened.
并且你很快就会承认的
And the sooner you admit it,
很快你的眼神里也就不会再有疑惑
the sooner you might get that haunted look out of your eyes.
听我说
Listen to me.
在那个时候  如果你幸存下来 对大家反而意味着结束
Sometimes surviving can be its own death sentence.
我知道的
I know that.
那么攻击那维克飞船的...
So the attack on Novacek's ship,
那个击伤他座机的
the one that winged him
还有当时雷达上显示的两个信号
and the two dradis contacts that were following him,
他们不是陶伦星人 是赛昂人攻击的
they weren't Taurons. Those were the Cylons.
这些年来  我跟自己说
For all those years, I told myself
我不知道他们是谁
that I didn't know what they were.
我只能这样骗自己
But I was just lying to myself.
假装那不是真的
Pretending that it couldn't be true.
那是真的
It is true.
是我开启了战争
I started it.
是我引发的
Initiated it.
等会儿
Wait a minute.
你开启了什么?
You started what?
引发了什么?
Started what?
对殖民地联邦的进攻
The attacks on the Colonies.
因为我越过了停火线
By crossing the line,
我让它们以为...
I showed them that
我们是群好战分子
we were the warmongers
就如它们所说的
they figured us to be.
并且我...
And I...
我让它们别无选择
I left them but one choice.
只有攻击我们
To attack us
在我们攻击它们前
before we attacked them.
不 不
No. No.
因为那不只是因为你
Because it wasn't just you.
是他们让你去那的
They put you there.
是他们让你去那越过停火线的 你没有选择的余地
They put you there, across the line. You had no choice.
那是军部的命令 那是...军队的命令
That was the Admiralty. That was the... That was the military.
你是在执行一个任务
You were one mission.
你只是一个人
You were one man.
一个人
One man.
只担当自己作为其中之一的责任
It only takes one.
你还好吗?
CAPRICA SIX: You're all right?
很好  当然
Yeah, of course.
做了更多的噩梦?
More nightmares?
梦
Dreams.
尽管这次有点不同
Something different this time, though.
我想上帝准备告诉我一些事情
I think God's trying to tell me something.
是关于盖尤斯  是吗?     不
It's about Gaius, isn't it? No.
不是的
It's not.
是关于一些更重要的
It's about something much bigger than that.
在你执行这个命令后
After you execute this command,
你要从你的日志中删除这个命令
you'll delete the order from your logs
并覆盖相应的存储位置
then overwrite the corresponding memory locations.
执行
Execute.
没事了 没事了
BOOMER: It's okay. It's okay.
放松  试着呼吸
Relax, try to breathe through it.
呼吸
Breathe.
噢  在生死之间
This is something beautiful.
有很美丽的景象
Miraculous, between life and death.
嗯
Hmm.
真是不可思议
That's weird.
为什么他妈的他们一直没有击中?
Why the hell do they keep missing?
妈的
Frak.
阿达玛
Adama.
上将  那维克中尉给你电话
DUALLA: Admiral, you have a call from Lieutenant Novacek.
把他接过来    比尔吗?
Put him through. NOVACEK: Bill?
是的?        我是丹尼尔
Yes? This is Danny.
我们需要谈谈    等会
We need to talk. Hold on.
我想现在就见到你
I need to see you right now.
等会 我马上就会过去
Hold on. I'll be right there.
是赛昂人给他装备的
The Cylons are saddled up on him.
它们的射击很完美 没有偏一丁点
They've got a perfect point-blank, no-deflection shot.
它们应该能让他毙命的
They had him dead to rights.
我想是吧
I'd say so.
听着  那维克被击中了  还冒着烟  还能飞得很直很水平
Look, Novacek was hit and smoking, flying straight and level.
一块金属片就该能要了他的命
Any nugget could make that kill.
赛昂人不应该浪费那么多次机会的 但是他们没杀了他
The Cylons could've wasted him any number of times, and they didn't.
它们没杀他 它们让他跑了
They didn't. They let him escape.
赛昂人没有做什么是让人很意外
The Cylons don't do anything by accident.
没错  这就是我在想的
Yeah, that's what I was thinking, too.
那维克有没有说他是怎样
Did Novacek say
从赛昂人监狱里跑出来的?
how he was able to overcome the Cylons that were holding him prisoner?
他们都生病?  中了病毒?
They were sick? Had a virus?
我的意思是  赛昂人中了多少种病毒  长官?
I mean, how many viruses do the Cylons have, sir?
谁知道呢? 可能是同一种病毒
Who knows? Maybe it was the same virus
就是我们发现的那些赛昂人得的
those Cylons we found were suffering from.
那好  也许他们只是在给我们编个故事  让我们上当呢
Yeah, or maybe they just told us a story that we'd buy.
一些我们很相信很熟悉的故事
Something that was credible, familiar.
那维克被基地之星关了三年
Novacek was held prisoner on a baseship for three years,
他逃出来了  并且很容易的找到了我们的舰队
escapes, and then conveniently finds our fleet
毫无根据的毫无理由的在这出现
with no agenda and no reason to be here.
嗨  丹尼尔
Hey, Dan.
平时训练的都报答给你了  这很有意思啊
NOVACEK: It's funny how all the training comes back.
对吧?
Huh?
为什么要骗我  比尔?
Why did you lie to me, Bill?
这些年来...
All those years,
你知道我是怎么跟自己说的吗?
you know what I kept telling myself?
那是我做的多么愚蠢  多么该死的梦?
What stupid, frakked-up dream I held onto?
我一直在想
I kept thinking,
"只要挺下来  大狗"
"Just hang in there, Bulldog.
"比尔・阿达玛快来了"
"Bill Adama's coming.
"他不会让你困在这里的  那不是他
"He won't leave you to rot in here, not him.
他是不会让任何人落下的"
He won't leave a man behind.
"只要坚持住"  但你没来救我
"Just hold on. " But you weren't coming.
你没想过我还活着 你都没有期望过我能活下来!
You didn't think I was alive. You weren't even hoping I was alive!
如果我没找到逃出去的方法
And if I hadn't figured a way to escape,
如果我在看到它们没把门关上的时候 没采取行动
if I didn't make my move when I saw they left that door wide open for me,
我现在肯定已经是条尸体!
I'd be as good as dead right now!
是它们留的吗?
Is that what they did?
是它们让门敞开着?
Did they leave the door standing open?
是它们让你逃出来的?
Did they let you escape?
那不是我说的意思
That's not what I meant.
我知道发生了什么
I know the truth.
是我打败了他们  你懂吗?
I beat them. Do you understand?
我在和它们的周旋中打败了它们
I beat them at their own game.
我杀死了该死的她  然后逃了出来
I frakking killed her, and I escaped.
你不承认我是自己逃出来的?!
You trying to take that away from me?
大狗!
TIGH: Bulldog!
蹲着!
Stay down!
你还好吗  比尔?
Are you all right, Bill?
是的  我还好
Yeah, I'm okay.
你不想承认  是吗?   我知道
You don't wanna believe it, do you? I know.
现实很难接受  大狗
The truth hurts, Bulldog,
但是活在真相里要比活在谎言里更好
but it's better to know the truth than to live a lie.
我们都是士兵  丹尼尔
We're all soldiers, Danny.
我们都要面对牺牲的
We're all expendable.
并且我们做了不得不做的事情 来保护任务的机密性
And we did what we had to do to protect the mission.
这很不好听  但事实如此  但赛昂人放了你出来
It's ugly, but there it is. The Cylons let you go.
这是为什么呢?  你自己扪心自问  丹尼尔
The question is, why? Ask yourself that, Danny.
因为在一分钟以前
Because up until a minute ago,
你就在做它们想让你做的事
you were doing exactly what they wanted you to do.
来到这里知道真相并寻仇
Come here and learn the truth and seek revenge.
并且那就是你正在做的事
And that's exactly what you did.
你差点就让它们的计划得逞了
You almost gave them what they wanted.
告诉你个不好的小秘密:
Tell you a dirty little secret.
一个人最难忍受的事
The toughest part of getting played
就是丧失你的尊严
is losing your dignity.
感觉就像是你喘气都没价值了 你会倒下来
Feeling like you are not worth the oxygen you are sucking down.
你会习惯的
You get used to it.
你会开始相信的
You start to believe it.
你会开始喜欢上的
You start to love it.
就像一瓶永远也喝不完的酒
It's like a bottle that never runs dry.
你可以伸手去拿很多很多很多次
You can keep reaching for it over and over and over again.
那你现在把酒瓶子丢了吗  少?
So, how do you put that bottle away, Saul?
我不知道
I don't know.
有一天你会决定...
One day, you just decide to
站起来走出自己的房间
get up and walk out of your room.
这是什么?
ROSLIN: What is this?
你的辞职书 你肯定是在和我开玩笑
Your resignation? You have gotta be kidding me.
我以前说过...
I've said before,
我们不能隐瞒自己所做过的事情
we can't hide from the things that we've done.
在这种情况下我别无选择
I see no other way around this situation.
也许是时候了  劳拉
Maybe it's time, Laura.
坐下  比尔
Sit down, Bill.
我认为你很天真
I think you're being naive.
天真?
"Naive"?
你有没有想过军部是故意让你
Did it ever occur to you that the Admiralty
去挑起一场他们谋划的战争?
may have set you up to provoke a war they wanted?
去想像那些我们不能理解的可怕的事情
It's naive to think that horrible things that we can't understand
有个简单的解释就是天真
have simple explanations.
因为简单的解释让我们感觉上是控制了实际并未控制的事情
Because simple explanations make us feel like we have control when we don't.
我们知道赛昂人为什么攻击我们
We know why the Cylons attacked us,
这肯定不是因为某一个原因就造成的    噢  我的天呐
and it wasn't any one thing. Oh, my Gods!
我们做过数以千计的事情
We did a thousand things,
有好的也有不好的
good and bad,
在这40年的每一天里都有  是这些事情使我们最后被攻击
every day for 40 years to pave the way for those attacks.
那也该做点什么
Something has to be done.
你知道这是什么吗?
You know what that is?
荣誉勋章
Medal of distinction.
这是在我听说你要辞职以前就准备好的
This was before I heard about this resignation of yours.
所以...
So...
我更愿意进行这项活动
I'd like to propose this.
你看起来很固执 在为什么东西而赎罪
You seem hell-bent on paying some kind of penance
为了那些你自认为做过的事情
for whatever it is you think you've done.
所以不要辞职了 你何不走出这里
So instead of resigning, why don't you get up and walk out of here,
明晚在飞行甲板的这个典礼上来见我
meet me on the port hangar deck tomorrow evening for this ceremony,
并让我把勋章别在你的胸口?
and let me pin a frakking medal to your chest?
我做不到
I can't.
不是为了你
It's not for you.
是为了他们
It's for them.
站在那里  让你的舰队知道
Stand up there, acknowledge your fleet,
做他们所期望的
and give them what they need.
一个英雄
A hero.
这才是你的赎罪方式
That'll be your penance,
就算它能毁了你
even if it kills you.
我谨代表全体人员很荣幸地给你
ROSLIN: On behalf of everyone in this room, it is my pleasure to present you,
阿达玛上将
Admiral Adama,
颁发荣誉勋章
with the medal of distinction
以纪念你45年来英勇无畏的为殖民地联邦舰队效力
for your 45 years of courageous service to the Colonial Fleet.
祝贺你
Congratulations.
你一到那里就让苏菲医生打我电话
Have Dr. Stoffa call me as soon as you arrive.
还有  大狗  你会好起来的
And, Bulldog, you're gonna be fine.
只要记住还需要点时间   好
Just remember it'll take some time. All right.
中尉
Lieutenant,
你忘了些东西
you forgot something.
我办不到 比尔 我...      穿上它
I can't. Bill, I... Take it.
你别想那么容易就脱下它
You're not getting off that easy.
一日机师  终生机师  大狗
Once a pilot, always a pilot, Bulldog.
是  长官
Yes, sir.
请进
ADAMA: Come in.
我听说你得了个勋章
I heard you won a medal.
是的
Yeah.
他们这些天把所有东西都发下去了
They give them out for anything these days.
模范行为
Good behavior,
全勤 与别人友好相处
attendance, playing well with others.
我想让你回到作战指挥中心
I need you back in the CIC.
没有你在那儿胁迫同僚就是不一样
It just ain't the same without you in there intimidating the inmates.
不
No.
那不是我想过来跟你说的
That's not what I came here to talk to you about.
好的
Okay.
那你来干吗?
So, why are you here?
我不知道 没什么
I don't know. Nothing.
你想告诉我艾伦发生了什么吗?
You wanna tell me what happened to Ellen?
我想喝点
I could use a drink.
我也是
Me, too.